soft engineering radio episode 110 rolls
in software engineering part 2 this is
software engineering radio the podcast
for professional developers on the web
at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support
[Music]
hello listeners welcome to part two of
the rolls episodes hello Michael
hello Marcus once again michaelis runs a
responsible mostly for the content and I
do the questioning so let me briefly
summarize what we did in the last
episode we basically talked about the
roles and the skills and the
competencies and the mindsets of the
junior developer the senior developer
and the architect in some sense you
could argue that those are the backbone
of the software development effort but
of course there are a lot of additional
kinds of people and roles that we need
and this is what we're going to talk
about in this episode so then just to
give you a quick overview we're going to
talk about the technologists and about
the team lead about the requirements
engineer but the product manager and the
project lead or project manager and
let's start off with a technologist I
guess the technologist as the name
implies has some very specific knowledge
about very specific technologies and
maybe concepts or approaches right right
technologists really focuses on the
technology as the name implies and this
is basically not the architect the guy
who knows most about the technology and
is in love with the technology shouldn't
be the architect so that is also
motivation for me to really separate
those two
and with the technologist we
differentiate and this is based on a
discussion we had before between the
evangelists and and a technology
consultant so how how do you see the
difference between between those two
well I guess the the technology
consultant actually focuses on solving
real problems in real projects whereas
the evangelist
typically has more of a marketing /
probe again
/ convinced potential customers role so
he works with nice examples he
communicates a lot he he comes up with a
lot of powerpoints it explains things
whereas the technology consultant really
I mean really uses the technology in
real mission critical environments so in
the general tasks of the tech
technologists would be to always be on
up-to-date on the latest technologies
relevant in his certain field so I think
it's impossible to know about every kind
of technology but to be up-to-date on
them under relevant technologies
programming languages application
servers or whatever in in his domain and
that would be the expectation and what I
also see with the technologies
technologist is that he runs two
evaluations in the context of a given
project and or ordi the organisation and
here it's it's quite important to know
your constraints to know what are the
limiting factors what is the budget
after project what is the timeline and
do I add sufficient time to build up the
knowledge with the developers to
developers know already and the
technology or do I have an risk here and
so it's really make those evaluations
with a with a broad context where you
involve all all the stakeholders this
makes things complicated but having
thought one's a bit broader saves you
the risk and and tedious efforts
afterwards right and then of course
another task is to actually help project
that struggle with the given technology
or that think about introducing a
certain technology actually introducing
it and and help them get up to speed
with it and and maybe also solve
problems in which they run into as they
as the project
progress is right yeah and as a as a
junior developer you might realize that
at a certain point in your career that
instead of designing over and over new
new solutions new features to your
project to your solution you find it
more interesting to learn about new
technologies to talk about those
technologies to dig deeper into the
concepts behind the technologies so that
is the point where you might want to
think about becoming a technologist
whereas I seldomly
see the pure role of the technologies
technologist within a company but very
often you would end up as a consultant
maybe even for for the vendor of a
certain technology and and so that would
be the start for your consulting career
at the end so what are some of the
skills skills is of course how would you
expect it differently
quick quick fast understanding of new
technologies new concepts the curiosity
driven to an extreme the curiosity to
learn
and taken to every new technology that
you get your hand on ok the next skill
that I can think of as is communication
skill because you need to be good and
explaining others the concepts the
technology right slides make PowerPoint
presentations write up simple examples
and and show them to others to to teach
others and the mindset I guess play
child right yeah play child constantly
find it under search for new playgrounds
for DES and then it becomes this special
for the Evangelist he really likes to
talk and demo endless talks Maya
I'd think about all the evangelists that
I met or listened to in the past think
for example on about Don box on hum or
later net there are plenty of examples
where the evangelists just is so
convinced he lives in that world and
cannot imagine any other world at least
that is how he gets perceived by by the
audience which is the whole point right
I mean you want your audience to believe
that you live for and breathe for this
stuff okay and the technology consultant
Eden really likes to solve real problems
but of course with his concrete
technology so he likes to stay with the
technology and when the technology is
not applicable he might move on to the
next job to the next opportunity now
okay I guess that concludes the
technologist yeah
next is the team lead but the the team
lead would basically lead a development
team with with junior developers senior
developers architect and and this really
depends on your project setup and
organization how you define a team lead
so it's not the guy with the official
directs yeah so the team lead would have
disciplinary rights he would have the
the developers has direct reports to him
so skills skills there is something of
course it's leadership but what is
leadership at the end it's like for me
at one part of it this is assertiveness
and I have to strength to follow up on
your promises next is really an interest
in the people in the in the growth of
every party and that is this is then
becomes already your your kind of
mindset hmm so I I jump to the mindset
briefly this is help everybody to be
good in their job and help everybody to
get better every day yeah down to this
coaching thing
this is coaching this is coaching unis
have a blend for for every team member
how to raise them how to to educate them
how to give them the challenges they
need so that they can grow on it right
then again if we talk about coaching
that does not mean that you actually
trained them every day you're the one
who manages their growth in their career
again go back to the manager tools
podcast they have very specific advice
on how to do coaching as opposed to
training I think and I guess you agree
they have really interesting stuff to
say in this context right they have
plenty of tools and well the podcast is
called manager tools and
really tools m4 for the team Laden in
this case next next kill I I like to
talk about this courage be strong and
enough to make tough decisions and give
honest feedback to your team members
with tough decisions you don't mean
technical decisions you mean decisions
like I don't know you know you're not
very well suited for this team why don't
you go somewhere else things like that I
don't know when then you shouldn't have
accepted this guy in your team in the
first place or give him a task that that
he can really perform on but at the end
when you realize well this the sky it
just has has changed his interests and
the project organization is no longer
his first interest then yet there is the
the the tough call necessary and say so
this is the direction that we as
organization like to follow are you with
us or are you out
I just wanted to distinguish it from
technology technological and project
decisions which are done by the
architect yeah I know but this this is
always like a very sensitive topic so I
try to given careful and cautious
explanation for you where you have a
social responsibility for the guys that
are with guys and girls that are with
you that are in your team but also you
have an employer interest and and really
having a high-performing team and
everybody committed to the same same
goals and when that is endangered you
you are asked to to make decisions yes
expect yeah go ahead and yet this is
different from technology decisions that
you better leave to your senior
developer and architect and not make the
technical decisions by yourself for
the team so the team lead should he have
been a developer or is it okay if he is
like I don't know a manager or however
you get become one I like team leads
personally that have an experience in in
software development because only then
they they truly understand how a
software developer feels what a pain
daily is what what testing means what
what kind of potential careers the
subordinates might aspire and have a
have a good gut feeling for the material
and at the end of the day you also
responsible for the result of it and
with that it it helps having having a
good knowledge about it know exactly
what the guys are doing and living and
breathing every day mm-hmm okay makes
sense anything else to add to the no I
think we we are through with the team
late we had the mindset already really
be the people person okay yeah so next
one is the requirements guy engineer or
analyst yeah with the requirements
analyst like we leave now this software
developer kind of track the technical
track the solution track we can render
more now as we said in the PLA episodes
to the problem space right so the
requirements guys are the problems they
deal with the problem should deal with
the solutions and well if they if they
deal with the solutions they become the
problem yes so what are the skills so
why don't you first explain briefly what
this guy does
so people so do require your analyst he
would talk to the customer translate the
customer language in in a technical
proper concrete and
not how would I how should I say it and
in a unique communication way so that
the the requirements are clear what I
want to say the data requirements must
be precise at the end of the day and all
the vagueness and uncertainty that the
customer has in his demands and there's
Bish's you should filter out but not
filter out by your own decision but ask
the customer that many questions still
until you are kind of sure what he
really meant means I mean we all know at
the end of a broad shake the customer
has meant it differently and has still
many more wishes that you can always
only resolve when you give them really a
chance to give feedback and show him in
the prototype or similar things yeah let
me briefly add to that three comments
first comment would be that yes of
course we know and we are aware of the
fact that you can only really solve all
the inconsistencies in requirements once
you actually implement but there is you
know there would be the developer but
there is still a lot of stuff the
requirements analyst has to do to clean
up inconsistencies and and stuff that
doesn't make any sense together
I have seen many requirements analysts
who basically just wrote down all the
crap the customer told them and that's
not very helpful they have to do
actually as you said they have to filter
things they have to make things
consistent and and find out stuff that
doesn't go together yes and the final
comment is that of course in a more
agile environment you do this extremely
iteratively you might write you know
stories or whatever you call these
things so we don't you know we don't say
that you have to do this big design or
big analysis upfront but somebody needs
to do that okay so starting off with the
skills it's I would start off with
creativity and finding new ways of how
to how to address the customer problems
because there
he already that the requirements analyst
makes already decisions on how the
solution in in what kind of direction it
will evolve with every statement with
every sentence he shapes the potential
solutions based he does the he's
involved in the scoping right when we
get to the product manager he'd really
dustin the scoping for what what a
product what kind of features are in and
out but at a detailed level the
requirements analyst when describing a
feature kevo he makes already conscious
choices on what to support what not to
support so creativity and solution
finding is really a skill necessary and
next this is one of the most important
things organizing things getting the the
world structured getting it consistent
being in love with with ordered things
and next is also that analyzes skills be
able to dig down into the domain
envision potential solutions on
usability make decisions know the
consequences on usability so usability
kind of kicks in depending on whether
you have explicit usability engineers or
whether us and requirements analysts
ever ready to to ensure the usability
you mentioned the idea or this this
concept of explaining things I found
that very useful if you're the
requirements person actually turn around
and explain to the customer what you
understand from what they just told you
that helps clarify things quite a bit so
you have to be able to to communicate
what you just learned in an inner inner
in a cleared up way
next sister and the knowledge the
competencies and here the domain
experience is something that that you
should really have because without
really knowing the customers to the main
of the customers you're not really good
and in elaborating and writing down the
requirements for potential solutions in
that domain so there this is I guess
more important than the the software
developer background where we had
already a brief discussion at the
beginning whether a software development
background is necessary or not I guess
it is helpful but sometimes it can also
lead you on the wrong track that you
specify solutions and not problems so
domain experience is something and the
knowledge about concepts and and maybe
also potential technologies and their
limitations because you will have to
state some some ill-at-ease
and doing it just Langley without any
technology understanding you won't be a
good sparing partner for for the
architect the architect should have the
responsibility and knowledge about the
technology that is in focus which could
be potentially be used and how he could
fulfill the ill-at-ease with it but I
mean it's it's always a good thing when
there is a conscious choice and
negotiation and discussion with the
requirement analyst on on those topics
with the architect so this is the
requirements our engineer would talk
with the architect and the architect
with the requirements engineer this is
one connection that I already see yeah
so I guess it's it's useful or maybe
even necessary that also for the
requirements guy the person should have
been a developer before yeah I mean it
helps definitely there's some danger as
I said but he generally I believe it
helps
- if we are in the software and software
behaves different and they're not our
typical hardware construction projects
it it's better if you understand it and
then respect that something just during
development has a high risk and that you
that you cannot plan and layout once and
and and years ahead of what you what you
will achieve but yet you have to respect
and understanding for the development
team that there are uncertainties that
some times it's just pure research that
those guys are doing and that they might
end up saying after two iterations or so
while we can't do it that way
think think of another way on how to
achieve this usability because it's this
technology Yvonne supported because work
is too expensive or whatever yep so
what's the mindset off of the
requirements analyst get the most
customer value for the cost and so
really be thinking about what what is
the consequence of getting it developed
this way I want to get out the most
features the most functionality the most
customer value satisfaction out of what
the development costs and this is
something that that us requirements
engineer even more so as a product
manager can influence and this is
something that that's pretty hard to
know the business the customers value of
a certain feature but only that at the
end really is the the determining metric
on the to drive to decisions it's not
what what a person individual person
likes it's what you can get out on
customer value at the end of the day so
you're also the one who prioritizes
requirements who assigns a risk to them
and
helps the customer together well
together with a customer you then decide
which of those requirements actually go
into a product or into an iteration yes
I've never been in a situation where we
managed all potential features we always
needed to prioritize and here a
requirements engineer he really helps
and dust the prior sation from the
customer point of view okay so I guess
the product manager to some extent is a
very senior requirements engineer is
that fair to say
that's a senior requirements engineer as
we define it here of course there are
different interpretations and
definitions floating around the product
manager as the name says is responsible
for one or several products and keeps an
eye on the focus is responsible for the
the scope of the development going on
and saying this is n this is odd and I
need to have it developed within this
time frame then I can market it else it
will be too late and this are the
mandatory features those are optional
and we even have typically contact maybe
even a group of requirements engineers
that is then further specifying and
detailing the features right skills
visionary thinking be able to
communicate with all kind of
stakeholders be able to perfectly speak
the customer language and then basically
and now we get into some some scrum OHL
methodology and terminology the Europe
product owner you own this product it's
your baby you take care of it you need
to take care that it survives and that
you spend your available money and the
money is mostly the the resources the
the effort of the development team wise
and to get the most out of it so I guess
then this guy in classical product
development is like the
the proxy for the potential customers
yeah he's the customer proxy yeah and he
also probably then has to have it a good
understanding of the market so he I mean
if you do a real project then you have
one customer and you can just ask him
whether he wants a feature or not and
then you have to prioritize it but if
you develop a product then your job is
also the market analysis to find out
which of the features are important for
a you know for the biggest possible
subset of the potential customers or you
know however you should say that yeah so
the manager is says the customer
viewpoint within an organization yeah
okay the mindset for the knowledge we
had already he should be he says senior
requirements engineer and just more
experience more breath before the
mindset challenge the development
department challenge to architect
challenge them to find a cheapest
solution for the best customer value I
mean cheap not in the sense of of low
quality by Johnson to to apply bright
matte ISM to not invest in things that
you can never sell where you never have
a benefit you we are with you
reusability can you ever say sell
reusability to a customer most probably
not
I agree but but I mean we're getting
into this product line discussion right
yeah we're getting into the product line
discussion so we can put it to an end I
mean reusability when the customer
really cares about it yeah when you
develop a platform that your customers
then using to build products on top of
it but as long as you would have no open
interfaces as long as you don't provide
a platform to the customer the customer
won't be able really to appreciate your
reuse and so it's mostly an
effectiveness topic within your own
organization right that's the point you
might have several customers with
similar but not identical
products and then you know
it might make your development efforts
just soar after a certain number of
development Dell checks with a similar
scope right okay just one comment since
we say the product manager is a senior
requirements engineer and since we say
the requirements engineer has to have
been a developer this implies that the
product owner sorry the product manager
also has been a developer I am I have
seen it differently in practice I'm not
absolutely sure here I would qualify
that I'm not sure if you agree but I
would say the guy has to have been with
the development team for long enough so
he understands the constraints of
software development but I've seen a lot
of product managers who have never been
developers and there are still good
product managers I agree I mean they're
you you have to requirements engineer
who is who at the end of the day can can
support you in making more software or
solution space space oriented decisions
as a product manager you first have to
be visionary you have to have the
customer focus you must have the cost of
business value focus and of course you
should get feedback from from the
architect to get a get a sanity check
from various peers and stakeholders and
yes the the other mmm skills and and
mindset is more important than your
software development background okay
this brings us to the last of the roles
which is the project leader or project
manager right so what's this guy doing
yes are his tasks or her tasks this guy
ensures that the development stays
within the given time cost and content
promises that the team development team
gave he tracks
those those efforts those achievements
and leads the project to a hopefully
positive end so it's that more an
organizational role hmm I wouldn't call
it organizational role it's really a
project focus so the project has a
certain duration it hasn't start it has
an end
it hasn't goal it has a cost plan what
it's supposed to cost what's the
available and that's a necessary effort
and he needs to to control and steer
actively steer those efforts make
decisions whenever there's a decision
necessary a trade-off to be to be made
and drive the project through help to
resolve obstacles yeah exactly that so
um skills you should know that the
template by now so skills yeah so should
he have been a developer once yes no I
guess yes at least a junior for some
time knowing what what yeah what what's
the the properties of software how the
software behave don't be disappointed
when it doesn't behave as your last
Hardware construction project and get
frustrated know the domain knows no
software development and I guess you can
only know it when when you lift once
it's in it so the skills it's it's
assertiveness be really strict when when
you need to be strict stay with your
decisions and and drive them through
your the bad conscience of a project and
you should find the weak spots put the
finger and get to the ground get
transparency make decisions together
with with the stakeholders but I guess
your manager will they'll keep they'll
hold you responsible for the success of
failure of of a project
networking networking because again you
have no typically no disciplinary rights
on on your colleagues so you have to
rely on on your network on your
communication skills how to convince and
get the job done
this sounds to me a little bit like this
matrix stuff that the manager tools guys
talked about in an episode in June oh
wait right did you hear that
I'm not sure can you elaborate well I
just talked about the matrix
organization where the person who
actually is the official boss that you
know the the disciplinary boss of people
is not the same person as the Project
Lead and therefore there is this matrix
of people and and because as they say a
matrix organization attenuates power
networking is extremely important so you
can actually make yourself heard and
make make thing get things done yeah so
it's exactly that point they're people
everybody has a boss an organizational
and disciplinary boss and then there's
the project and within the organization
where the boss the project boss is the
Project Lead yeah and by the way the
manager got tools guys hate metrics or
organizations competencies competencies
yes and this is the reason why I said
well have some of the developer
background because you should know about
software development processes no
software development processes with
their con the consequences with the
benefits and trade-offs how to to select
the right process for the for the
project and know how to constantly
improve for your process okay the Nexus
metrics here again a good software
understanding helps you to find the
right metrics on on back reports on
quality metrics on test coverage
tricks that really that that help you to
achieve transparency the transparency
that you need to make decisions that you
do based on that you base on your
decisions because very often you will be
faced with situations where you mmm it's
like a look like a black hole but like a
black box where you can't really view in
like during an iteration when when guys
are using HR methodologies iterative
incremental development processes within
an iteration it's very often not
transparent what to stare does what the
result will be and there you just need
to trust on on metrics on what what does
the bill say what is the what it will
then most probably be the final result
of an iteration hopefully you add that
much trust that you can wait till the
end of literation if you want to know
more what's going on watch the metrics
alternatively you can also make the
iteration very short that gives you more
inside yeah but then everybody will
complain about a huge we planning effort
every every other week and so you will
need to find a trade-off with the
development team on the duration length
so just to say this very clearly the
project lead or project manager is the
person who is responsible for the
process may be supported by some you
know process coach in the same sense as
we've had the technologist for
technologies but he's the owner of the
process so my inside set mindset I put
it that way every might stop slippage is
a private failure you mean a personal
failure personal failure I mean this is
pretty tough and exaggerated but I know
guys who live it that way and
well it's not fun being in their project
sometimes it's it's demanding but then
also very satisfying when you really
achieve it and they guys those guys they
know how to achieve it so you're going
to be successful with them they will be
a pain in the neck for you they will
challenge you they will try to get
transparency on an any issue but this is
good to the Southie and you will have
successful projects hopefully okay I
guess this this this was the last of the
roles right this was the last of the
roles and now coming back to a to an
promise we we made at the beginning of
the first rolls episode this was how
disease actually met to an HL
environment right now now are those
roles totally mmm crap and in an HR
context would you throw everybody off
board and say well we don't need a
project lead anymore we don't have a
requirements engineer we only have those
team and the scrum master and of course
yes you need some some product owner the
product so we start off with the product
owner product owner is somebody like a
project manager product manager and
requirements engineer but a product
owner at least when you really scale up
he's also responsible for for the
overall timeline keeping keeping an eye
on the timeline on the quality he will
either accept or reject a delivery of a
feature team so there's also something
of a of a project lead in a in a product
owner so that is and in product owner
has to be specific is a trademark term
from the scrum so I will for either
scrum product owner here then within the
team I guess you have to test her
you have of course developers you most
probably will have an architect this
architect I don't know sometimes he's
really within a scrum team sometimes he
might be shared it depends on your
working model so those roles are still
valid also in a scrum context mmm so all
in all yeah the the roles are cut a bit
different but they still make sense and
you can find the meaningful mapping and
like having seen some some organizations
who transitioned to an HL methodology
the people were all needed at the end of
the day they sometimes were required to
have a different mindset so that you've
never changed a bit because you might
not realize so much more on the on the
strict definite definition of roles and
responsibilities but you you more rely
on on the team as it takes the
responsibility mmm there so how to
summarize it there is a mapping the
mapping you make sense and you can you
can really argue on the the mapping it's
meaningful it's it's not trivial
entrance transformations to HR our
successful when you really think on on
the mapping and make that a conscious
choice
okay so before we close down this second
episode let me add or ask about two
topics that came to my mind while we
while we recorded it
one is QA QA is more than testing I
guess I mean there's a lot of reviewing
going on there is maybe you know I mean
do you see QA Quality Assurance as a
separate thing or I mean what's your
opinion on that QA has two sides for me
I mean one is really the practical
aspect where they closely work together
with the testers sometimes they might
even test themselves I guess at least
that would be a good idea I think the
other is that they really take you up as
a development organization on your
promises on your process they ensure
that you stick to the process and for
example in some restricted or regulated
domains like the medical domain they
will also make sure that you comply with
your process to the regulations that so
that you are at the end of the
development allowed to release your
product to the corresponding market and
the second and promised final thing I
had was staffing who is responsible for
hiring new people what probably is not
the junior developers how do you
organize that where do you put that
responsibility it's the team lead and I
would suggest and really involving your
senior guys in the interviews checking
on the mindset checking on the chemistry
how how does this guy fit into the team
and they're involve your your seniors
getting feedback as a team lead or R&D
head I guess that's that's pretty common
standard good okay is there anything
else you want to add before we close
this down no I think we we went through
a whole set of of roles there there of
course more role
out there the ones that we didn't cover
we don't intend to say there they're not
important we just tried to have a
limited focus its current for her for
the end it's already recorded for about
96 98 minutes in a row so I guess it's
probably enough hopefully this is what's
worthwhile for you to listen to and you
got something out if you have any
thoughts and I guess there are many
thoughts please let us know on on the
website add some comment to the episode
we're looking forward to it
absolutely so thank you all for
listening thanks Michael for talking
thank you and talk to you next time bye
bye bye
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
solve the engineering radio soft
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at st - radio
dot length if you want to support us you
can donate to the AC radio team via the
website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team @ SC - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of SU radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
travel
[Music]